Fatih Sayin

Austin, TX 78729 | (512) 765 3221 | fmsayin@hotmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin/

GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io/

CAREER SUMMARY

Strategic, multidisciplinary Data Analyst with an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Combining my expertise in research methodology, project management, and administrative experience of 18 years with creative data analysis methods to deliver the best results. Aiming of collecting, cleaning, analyzing, visualizing, storing, and making meaningful highlights out of the data with the best tools available.

RELATED SKILLS

- Used fuzzy logic approach for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Proposed solutions to improve system efficiencies and reduce total expenses
- Presented data and analysis in order to improve strategies and operations in academic institutions
- Performed data-driven cultural research to highlight nuances between the general and target business
- Detail-oriented, thorough, initiative, solution-seeker, enthusiastic-friendly team member, and excellent in understanding collaborative project-management to achieve high demands.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization Graduated in 2019

Ivane Javakhishvili State University, Tbilisi, Georgia | Ph.D. in International Relations Graduated in 2009

Free University of Tbilisi, Georgia | BA in International Relations Graduated in 2000

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Python Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions
- Databases: MySQL, MongoDB
- SQL and SqlAlchemy
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, D3.js, Leaflet.j

MOST RECENT PROJECTS

Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code

Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib **Description:** Coded a Crime Data API python general script

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. Rental Movie Database
- Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub
- Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql challange

2. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

- Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables
- Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel

3. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

- Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude.

 Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather-Py

4. Name: VBA of Wall Street

- Tools Used: VBA, Advanced Excel, GitHub
- Analyzed Wall Street stock market data in VBA script language.
 Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/The VBA of Wall Street

5. Name: Heroes of Pymoli

Apr 2001 – Feb 2002

- Tools Used: Python, Pandas, Jupyter Notebook.
- Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a fantasy game. Generated a report that breaks down
 the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes of Pymoli

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE		
Jan 2019 – Present	Data and Business Analyst and Investment Consultant, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA	
Oct 2018 – Present	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin	
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Improving English Skills, Austin, Texas, USA	
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Adviser to the President, Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey	
Sep 2014 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of MIMER (The Alliance of Civilizations Research Center)	
- •	Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey	
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Department Chair and Assistant Professor Department of International Relations and Political Science, and IR, Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey	
Jun 2009 – Jul 2011	Assistant Professor, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Jul 2006 – Jun 2007	Founding Principal, Nikoloz Tsereteli International School, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Jul 2004 – Jun 2006	Founding Principal, Niko Nikoladze Secondary School, Kutaisi, Georgia	
Mar 2002 – Jul 2004	Director, Language Center (Enata Tsentri) Kutaisi, Georgia	
Apr 2001 –Feb 2002	Research Assistant, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Jul 2000 – Mar 2001	Director, Language Center (Enata Tsentri) Tbilisi, Georgia	
	ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE	
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Assistant Professor, Department of International Trade and Business Administration and	
- •	IR Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey	
Sep 2009 – Jul 2011	Assistant Professor, Department of Business Administration, International Black	
	Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	
Jul 2007 – Aug 2009	Lecturer, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia	

Research Assistant, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia

PUBLICATIONS

I have published 19 articles in peer review journals. My academic work includes several articles about the European Union, Caucasus, and Euro -Asia which are published in internationally recognized research journals. I edited the Dictionary of Georgian -Turkish / Turkish-Georgian, which is published in 2012 by International Black Sea University. My latest research focuses on comparative politics, the alliance of civilizations and conflict resolution for global problems. (Analysis of International Conflicts and Possible Solution, Methods Using Fuzzy Logic as an Alternative Perspective) In particular I have been working on the inherent conflicts of political and cultural domination.

TEACHING EXPERENCE	
2013-2016	Research Methods
2015-2016	International Organizations
2014-2016	International Relations Theories
2014-2016	Introduction to International Relations
	GRANTS
2015-2016	Grant for Publications, Canik Basari University
2014-2015	Grant for Publications, Canik Basari University
2013-2014	Grant for Publications, Canik Basari University
	LANGUAGES
English	Full professional proficiency
Turkish	Native proficiency
Georgian	Full professional proficiency